window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Theory_of_Computation - Context_Free_Language — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Context_Free_Language — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(G_1, G_2 \\) be Context-Free Grammars (CFGs) and \\(R \\) be a regular expression. For a grammar \\(G \\), let \\(L(G) \\) denote the language generated by \\(G \\).\n<br>\nWhich ONE among the following questions is decidable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) = L(G_2) \\)?</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) \\cap L(G_2) = \\emptyset \\)?</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) = L(R) \\)?</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) = \\emptyset \\)?</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Is \\(L(G_1) = \\emptyset \\)?</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460820/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-15#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following two languages over the alphabet \\(\\{a, b, c\\}\\), where \\(m\\) and \\(n\\) are natural numbers:\n<br><br>\n\\(L_1 = \\{ a^m b^m c^{m+n} \\mid m, n \\geq 1 \\}\\)<br>\n\\(L_2 = \\{ a^m b^n c^{m+n} \\mid m, n \\geq 1 \\}\\)\n<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the following statements is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both \\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are context-free languages.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is a context-free language but \\(L_2\\) is not a context-free language.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not a context-free language but \\(L_2\\) is a context-free language.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) are context-free languages.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not a context-free language but \\(L_2\\) is a context-free language.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460045/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-35#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following context-free grammar \\(G\\), where \\(S\\), \\(A\\), and \\(B\\) are the variables (non-terminals), \\(a\\) and \\(b\\) are the terminal symbols, \\(S\\) is the start variable, and the rules of \\(G\\) are described as:\n<br><br>\n\\(S \\to aaB \\mid Abb\\)<br>\n\\(A \\to a \\mid aA\\)<br>\n\\(B \\to b \\mid bB\\)\n<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the languages \\(L(G)\\) is accepted by \\(G\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^2b^n \\mid n \\geq 1 \\} \\cup \\{ a^n b^2 \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^n b^{2n} \\mid n \\geq 1 \\} \\cup \\{ a^{2n} b^n \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^n b^n \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^{2n} b^{2n} \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L(G) = \\{ a^2b^n \\mid n \\geq 1 \\} \\cup \\{ a^n b^2 \\mid n \\geq 1 \\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460071/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements is/are CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The intersection of two regular languages is regular.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The intersection of two context-free languages is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The intersection of two recursive languages is recursive.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The intersection of two recursively enumerable languages is recursively enumerable.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The intersection of two regular languages is regular.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The intersection of two recursive languages is recursive.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The intersection of two recursively enumerable languages is recursively enumerable.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399298/gate-cse-2023-question-14#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages:<br><br>\\( \\begin{aligned}\nL_1&amp;= \\{ ww|w  \\in  \\{a,b \\}^* \\}   \\\\\nL_2&amp;= \\{a^nb^nc^m | m,n \\geq 0 \\}  \\\\\nL_3 &amp;= \\{a^mb^nc^n|m,n \\geq 0 \\}\n\\end{aligned}\\)<br><br>Which of the following statements is/are FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is not context-free but \\(L_2\\) and \\(L_3\\) are deterministic context-free.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_2,L_3\\) and \\(L_2 \\cap L_3\\) all are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor its complement is context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_2,L_3\\) and \\(L_2 \\cap L_3\\) all are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor its complement is context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371898/Gate-cse-2022-question-38#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages:<br><br>\\( \\begin{aligned}\nL_1&amp;= \\{a^n wa^n|w  \\in  \\{a,b \\}^* \\}   \\\\\nL_2&amp;= \\{wxw^R | w,x  \\in   \\{a,b \\}^*, |w|,|x|  \\gt 0  \\}\n\\end{aligned}\\)<br><br>Note that \\(w^R\\) is the reversal of the string \\(w\\). Which of the following is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are regular.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\)  are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\)  are context-free but not regular.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are regular.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\)  are context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371899/Gate-cse-2022-question-37#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>For a string \\(w\\), we define \\(w^R\\) to be the reverse of \\(w\\). For example, if \\(w=01101\\) then \\(w^R=10110\\).\n<br>\nWhich of the following languages is/are context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxw^Rx^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{ ww^Rxx^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxw^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxx^Rw^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{ ww^Rxx^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxw^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{ wxx^Rw^R \\mid w,x \\in \\{0,1\\} ^* \\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357499/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-41#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(L_1\\) be a regular language and \\(L_2\\) be a context-free language. Which of the following languages is/are context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap \\overline{L_2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\overline{\\overline{L_1} \\cup \\overline{L_2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cup (L_2 \\cup \\overline{L_2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((L_1 \\cap L_2) \\cup (\\overline{L_1} \\cap L_2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\overline{\\overline{L_1} \\cup \\overline{L_2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cup (L_2 \\cup \\overline{L_2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((L_1 \\cap L_2) \\cup (\\overline{L_1} \\cap L_2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357528/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-12#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Suppose that \\(L_1\\) is a regular language and \\(L_2\\) is a context-free language. Which one of the following languages is NOT necessarily context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cap L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cdot L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 - L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\cup L_2\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 - L_2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357451/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages. <br>\\(L_1=\\{wxyx|w,x,y \\in (0+1)^+\\}\\) <br>\\(L_2=\\{xy|x,y \\in (a+b)^*,|x|=|y|,x\\neq y\\}\\) <br> <br>Which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) context- free but not regular and \\(L_2\\) is context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Neither \\(L_1\\) nor \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) context- free but  \\(L_2\\) is not context-free.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1\\) is regular and \\(L_2\\) is context- free.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333199/gate2020-cs-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider the language \\(L=\\{a^n|n\\geq 0\\}\\cup \\{a^nb^n|n\\geq 0\\}\\) and the following statements. <br><br>\nI. L is deterministic context-free.<br>\nII. L is context-free but not deterministic context-free.<br>\nIII. L is not LL(k) for any k.<br><br>\nWhich of the above statements is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>III only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333221/gate2020-cs-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following languages over \\(\\Sigma =\\{a,b\\}\\) is NOT context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{ww^R|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nb^nw^R|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nw^Rb^n|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^nb^i|i \\in \\{n,3n,5n\\},n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{wa^nw^Rb^n|w \\in \\{a,b\\}^*,n\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302817/gate2019-cs-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages: <br><br>I. \\( \\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{p}d^{q}|m+p=n+q, \\; where \\;  m,n,p,q \\geq 0 \\}\\)    <br>  II. \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{p}d^{q}|m=n \\; and \\; p=q, \\; where \\;  m,n,p,q\\geq 0 \\}  \\) <br> III. \\( \\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{p}d^{q}|m=n=p \\; and \\; p\\neq q, \\; where \\; m,n,p,q\\geq 0 \\} \\) <br>  IV. \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}c^{p}d^{q}|mn=p+q, \\; where\\;  m,n,p,q\\geq 0\\}\\) <br><br>Which of the languages above are context-free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>II and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204109/gate2018-35#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following languages<br><br> \\(L_{1}=\\{a^{p}|p\\) is a prime number} <br>\\(L_{2}=\\{a^{n}b^{m}c^{2m}|n\\geq 0,m\\geq 0\\} \\)<br> \\(L_{3}=\\{a^{n}b^{n}c^{2n}|n\\geq 0\\}\\)<br>\\( L_{4}=\\{a^{n}b^{n}|n\\geq 1\\}\\)<br><br> Which of the following are CORRECT ?<br><br>\nI.\\(L_{1}\\) is context-free but not regular. <br>\nII. \\(L_{2}\\) is not context-free. <br>\nIII. \\(L_{3}\\) is not context-free but recursive. <br>\nIV. \\(L_{4}\\) is deterministic context-free. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I ,II and IV only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118615/gate2017-2-40#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(L_{1},L_{2}\\) be any two context free languages and R be any regular language. Then which of\nthe following is/are CORRECT ?<br> I. \\(L_{1}\\cup L_{2}\\) is context - free <br>II. \\(\\bar{L_{1}}\\)  is context - free <br>III. \\(L_{1} - R\\) is context - free <br> IV. \\(L_{1}\\cap L_{2} \\) is context - free <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I, II and IV only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118143/gate2017-2-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
